 <section><title>Abitrary Hooks</title>
 <para>Building a callout API makes sense for common, structured
 features in software, but occassionlly there is a need to provide
 somewhat arbitrary hook points after the software is designed
 and the noit_hooks system is what satisfies this need.</para>
 <para>The design goals here are somewhat specific in that we
 would like to allow for a large number of hook points at low cost
 when not instrumented.  As such, a hash lookup of registered hooks
 would be considered to expensive.  Additionally, we want to provide
 strong, compile-time type safety as it can be all to easy to hook
 something with a function with a slightly incorrect protoype that
 could result in disasterous corruption or crashes (or perhaps worse
 daftly subtle bugs that are punishing to troubleshoot).</para>
 <para>The hooks system is simple a set of two macros; one allowing
 for the declaration of function prototypes for registering and invoking
 a specific programmer-specifiec instrumentation point and the other
 providing an implementation of the registration and invocation
 routines.  Due to the nature of C, the macro calling conventions are
 less than elegant, but ultimately require no complicated implementation
 by the programmer.</para>
   <section><title>Hook Declaration</title>
   <para>
   Declaring hooks is done by calling the NOIT_HOOK_PROTO macro with
   the name of the hook (a term that composes a valid C function name),
   the arguments it expects, the type of closure (usually a void *),
   and some variations on those themes that provide CPP enough info
   to construct an implementation with no programmer "programming."
   </para>
   <para>The declaration of a hook "foo" will yield in two functions:
   foo_hook_invoke and foo_hook_register.</para>
   <example>
   <title>Declaring a foobarquux hook in a header.</title>
   <para>A foobarquux hook prototype that takes a struct timeval * argument.</para>
   <programlisting>
     NOIT_HOOK_PROTO(foobarquux, (struct timeval *now),
                     void *, closure, (void *closure, struct timeval *now));
   </programlisting>
   </example>
   <example>
   <title>Implementing a foobarquux hook in source.</title>
   <para>A foobarquux hok implementation that takes a struct timeval * argument.</para>
   <programlisting>
     NOIT_HOOK_IMPL(foobarquux, (struct timeval *now),
                    void *, closure, (void *closure, struct timeval *now),
                    (closure,now));
   </programlisting>
   </example>
   </section>
   <section><title>Hook Usage</title>
   <para>Once the hook is implemented, it can be used by the application
   and instrumented by code at runtime. In the below example, we'll
   invoke the foobarquux instrumentation and assuming no issues arise,
   we'll invoke the original foobarquux_work() function.</para>
   <example>
   <title>Instrumenting a function conditionally.</title>
   <para>Before we instrument, suppose we have:</para>
   <programlisting>
     foobarquux_work();
   </programlisting>
   <para>Now we wish to allow programmers to add instrumentation
   immediately before this code that can conditionally prevent its
   executation:</para>
   <programlisting><![CDATA[
     struct timeval now;
     gettimeofday(&now, NULL);
     if(NOIT_HOOK_CONTINUE ==
        foobarquux_hook_invoke(&now))
       foobarquux_work();
   ]]></programlisting>
   </example>
   <para>If the hook should not conditionally cause or prevent code
   to run, the invoke function's return value can be ignored.</para>
   <para>In order to register a function that allows the above execution
   on every other subsequent execution one would provide the following:
   </para>
   <example>
   <title>A sample instrumentation of foobarquux</title>
   <programlisting>
     static my_sample_hook(void *closure, struct timeval *now) {
       static int alt = 0;
       return (alt++ % 2) ? NOIT_HOOK_CONTINUE : NOIT_HOOK_DONE;
     }

     ...
       foobarquux_hook_register("sample", my_sample_hook, NULL);
     ...
   </programlisting>
   </example>
   </section>
 </section>
 