<module>
  <name>collectd</name>
  <description><para>The collectd module provides collectd support for Reconnoiter.  The collectd modules listens on a UDP port and waits for metrics to come from a collectd agent. It also provides support for signing and encrypting metrics from the collectd agent, which is supported in version 4.7.0 and above.  Only one is supported per target.</para></description>
  <loader>C</loader>
  <image>snmp.so</image>
  <moduleconfig>
    <parameter name="collectd_port"
               required="required"
               default="25826"
               allowed="\d+">The port which collectd packets are received</parameter>
    <parameter name="snmptrapd_host"
               required="optional"
               default="*"
               allowed="\d+">The host interface on which packets are accepted.</parameter>
  </moduleconfig>
  <checkconfig>
    <parameter name="security_level"
               required="optional"
               allowed="\d+">An integer detailing the security level which to allow.  0 for all packets allowed, 1 for signed and encrypted packets allowed, 2 for only encrypted packets allowed.</parameter>
    <parameter name="username"
               required="optional"
               allowed=".+">The collectd username for authenticating signed and encrypted packets</parameter>
    <parameter name="password"
               required="optional"
               allowed=".+">The collectd password for authenticating signed and encrypted packets</parameter>
  </checkconfig>
  <examples>
    <example>
      <title>Simple encrypted passive checking.</title>
      <para>The following example allows a collectd agent to send any metric to the noit
      system.  In this example the collectd agent must be version 4.7.0 to support encryption 
      and must be configured with parameters similar to the ones below.  Like the snmptrap 
      module the collectd disregards the timeout value completely, but uses the period to
      batch all the checks in one commit.  If there are >1 metrics within the period the
      check is marked as G and A for state and availability respectively.</para>
      <programlisting><![CDATA[
      <Plugin network>
        <Server "127.0.0.1" "25826">
          SecurityLevel "encrypt"
          Username "us3rname"
          Password "s3cr3t"
        </Server>
      </Plugin>

      <noit>
        <modules>
          <module image="collectd" name="collectd">
            <config>
              <username>us3rname</username>
              <password>s3cr3t</password>
              <security_level>2</security_level>
            </config>
          </module>
        </modules>
        <checks>
          <check uuid="1b4e28ba-2fa1-11d2-883f-e9b761bde3fb" module="collectd"
                 period="60000" timeout="30000"/>
        </checks>
      </noit>
    ]]></programlisting>
    </example>
  </examples>
</module>
