<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % magic.fixup SYSTEM "http://labs.omniti.com/docbook/ent">
  %magic.fixup;
]>
<chapter id="arch.noitd">
  <title>noitd</title>
  <para>
    <command>noitd</command> is the "scout in the field."  It is responsible 
    for performing service checks and obtaining metric information from services
    on remote machines.  Typically, one <command>noitd</command> daemon is 
    deployed in each datacenter and is responsible for talking to each machine 
    and collecting service information.
  </para>
  <para>
    The <command>noitd</command> daemon should be positioned in the network 
    topology such that it has direct access to each machine it monitors (same 
    layer 2 segment).  This is a SHOULD, not a MUST.  <command>noitd</command> 
    can be used to monitor remote services as well (such as checking HTTP page 
    load times from one monitoring location to services running in another 
    datacenter).  The direct access is suggested for sensitive services that 
    should not be accessible from outside the network.
  </para>
  <para>
    The <command>noitd</command> daemon provides datafeed services to a 
    <command>stratcond</command> daemon over port 34332 (or another port of 
    your choosing) via an SSL-protected TCP transport.
  </para>
  <section id="arch.noitd.design">
    <title>noitd Design</title>
    <para>
      <command>noitd</command> is designed to be high-performance as well as
      easy to administer.  Clearly, ease of administration is a subjective
      assessment.  The goal in administration was to make the
      <command>noitd</command> system as much like a network device as
      possible.  The methodology and approach to use is very similar to other
      network devices such as switches and routers.  Telnet access (available
      over both SSL and non-SSL) provides access to a CLI that allows
      assessment of operation as well as reconfiguration.  It is designed to
      make network administrators feel "at home."
    </para>
    <para>
      The performance of <command>noitd</command> is grounded in its use of a
      hybrid event/thread and careful coding practices to ensure that blocking
      operations and computationally intensive operations are handled 
      asynchronously to non-blocking operations.
    </para>
    <para>
      The configuration system is entirely XML-based, providing two inheritance
      paradigms.  The first is provided by simple XML parent-child relationships
      such that required attributes that are unspecified in leaf nodes are
      resolved by walking up the element's ancestral stack.  The second model
      uses an explicit "inherit" attribute that allows for complicated 
      configuration information to be stored elsewhere in the XML tree for 
      readability and maintainability.  All configuration can be performed by 
      the CLI with a router-like syntax, so those uncomfortable with XML can 
      configure the system with equal ability.
    </para>
    <para>
      Checks are loaded into the system dynamically (through shared object 
      loading.) New checks can be authored and added to the system without 
      recompiling the host <command>noitd</command> daemon.  Some modules can 
      be loaded during runtime, but due to security concerns, super-user 
      privileges are dropped after module initialization.  This security 
      feature prevents the correct operation of any module requiring extended 
      privileges for initialization.  Adding such a module to the configuration 
      will require a restart of the <command>noitd</command> process.  The 
      ping_icmp module is an example of a module requiring extended privileges 
      for initialization (the opening of RAW network sockets.)
    </para>
    <para>
      In addition to checks implemented as dynamic objects (ELF or Mach) that
      are loaded into the system with dlopen() or similar such mechanisms,
      <command>noitd</command> allows for alternate "loader" implementations.  
      <command>noitd</command> has a "lua" loader that allows checks to be 
      scripts in the Lua programming language.
    </para>
  </section>
</chapter>
<!--
vim:ts=2:sw=2:et:
-->
